Hello, this is our web exclusive Q&A on
character, a companion video to Brandon
Sanderson's lecture series this year for
2025. Um, we have taken questions from
you that were put in the comments
section of the lecture on um character.
So, if you haven't watched that lecture,
you should and you should watch the
other character lectures because these
are going to be answering uh these are
going to be questions that I didn't
already answer. Questions that you might
have might have already been answered.
So, uh this is a companion piece um web
exclusive. Thank you for your questions.
We have selected 10 of them and I'm
going to get to them here. Brandon
touched briefly on the idea of common
arcs in his lecture when he brought up
the apprentice arc. I'd be curious to
hear him speak about some other common
arcs, maybe their defining
characteristics, like a little cheat
sheet for common character growth
directions. What an excellent question.
Um, if this method of storytelling helps
you, and it does help me, I recommend
that you start keeping a list of things
that you notice so that you can be like,
"Oh, this seems to be a common sort of
character arc. What are its defining
characteristics? What makes it work?
What do I like about it?" And that's
probably the most important part. which
sort of character arcs do you most like?
Um, and the apprentice arc is one of
them. Uh, the apprentice arc is
obviously apprentice and master. Uh,
kind of apprentice follows in the
master's footsteps. Um, and the fun
interplay in the apprentice arc is where
does the apprentice decide to deviate
from the master and where do they decide
to follow the master? What can they
accomplish the master can't? What could
the master accomplish that they can't?
And how do they have to approach it in
different ways? This is really great for
kind of separating two characters apart
that might have the same skill set as
you see one learn from the other and
make it their own. Um, and that's why I
love the apprentice arc because it
really can highlight a character uh and
show how they have to approach the world
differently from how a mentor might have
approached the world. Um, but there are
lots of different uh sorts of sorts of
character arcs that you can do. Um, one
of the kind of primary ones, um, is the
idea of you upfront show a character
being bad at something and then they
need to learn to fix it, right? Um, this
is kind of your classic character arc. A
character is shown to be prideful and
how do they get over their pride? Um,
you're just very classic. Usually with
these arcs, what you really want to do
is you want to show upfront how this
impacts their lives. you uh most things
that can be a flaw in a character can be
both an advantage and a disadvantage. Um
you know hubris can also just be
self-confidence. So you want to
establish early on look this is how the
way the person acts is causing them to
miss opportunities causing them to miss
growth causing them to their
relationships to fall apart or something
like this. and through the course of the
story. Then if it's an downward arc, you
show them learning this lesson but then
still refusing at the most important
moment to put it into
toxilization. It's not just about
someone is constantly arrogant and then
that causes them to fail at the end. It
is they know by this point that this is
their tragic flaw and they will not let
go of it at that important moment. Um or
you go the reverse. You show them
learning the lesson and then you have
that decision point and you show why
they would make the different choice and
that's the important thing uh where this
gets paint by numbers like oh I have to
have them you know fail to this thing
three times and then succeed that's not
interesting what's interesting is the
why who have they become why how have
they changed why is this why do we now
believe that this is the person that
they have become why would they make
this decision and that arc can be really
really satisfying um for a character but
there's There's so many different
things. Um, I really like the move from
ignorance to to knowledge. This is, you
know, your classic sort of mystery arc
uh done as a character where they learn
about themselves while they're learning
about a mystery in the
world. There's information they need to
have. They need to learn to be a better
or uh different person in order to
actually put that information uh into
place. uh spoiling an agatha Christie
novel. Uh Hercule Purau's uh final story
is about him learning that there are um
villains out there that are smart
enough. He cannot prove that they have
um that they have committed the crime.
He can know because he's smart enough to
do that, but he cannot find the proof.
And that character arc is a really
interesting one for a detective
realizing that you there there are cases
that you can solve but not prove that
you've solved and what that does to him
and the choices that he makes. Um this
is you know again a mystery being solved
while a character learns something about
themselves. So uh there's just a few of
them for you. Uh but be watching for
these. Uh have your your your book I
always joke that authors have a little
black book but it's not a name of uh
people that they have dated. It is uh
interesting character flaws that in the
people that they've met that they don't
tell them about but that they watch for
and watch how people overcome them so
that they can make use of those in
stories. How do you make a character's
arc in the first book of a series feel
complete and satisfying? When a
character has a lot to work on other
parts of themselves um but we'll do
which they'll do in potential sequels.
Um so uh this isn't this is a good
question and uh for this you'll need to
number one define if you are writing a
um an iconic character or not uh or a
character that becomes iconic. Uh, an
iconic character is one that
um has decided that you have decided has
primarily external arcs or they have
small internal arcs that do not
necessarily make big changes to who they
are book to book. Um, a lot of your
iconic heroes are people that large
series have been written about that you
can read out of order. Um, if you're not
writing that, um, and those are
perfectly valid sorts of stories to
write. Uh there's some very excellent
stories written about iconic heroes. Um
if you're not uh writing about that,
then what you're going to want to ask
yourself is um are there different
things the character needs to work on
about themselves? Um and are there
ramifications from the first book that
cause further complications? Uh the
thing that I don't like um and I find
that readers don't like is when you have
a character black backslide too much.
You can maybe get away with this once.
um where a character's made a decision
and in a future book they are the scope
of what that decision makes them live
with is um is bigger than they thought.
Uh the classic example of this is
Spider-Man 1 and two in the Samaran
trilogy. Um you know in Spider-Man 1,
Spider-Man decides to be a hero.
Spider-Man 2 has to live with being a
hero and that makes him question.
Spider-Man 2 is the strongest of that
trilogy. And that's in part because one
is expected and two is a really deep
look at what it actually costs someone
to have to do this and it makes him
question. You can't do that again. Uh at
least I feel like if you do that again,
it becomes a problem. And indeed, most
people who have a character backslide do
not do it as well as Sam Remy and his
writers did um with that trilogy. And so
I recommend looking and saying what's
the next step? Uh a good example again
of this from film that is not a
character arc but can help you
understand is um Star Wars the first
movie introduces Darth Vader as a
villain but it doesn't really have Luke
face him. The second film has Luke face
Darth Vader and fail. And the third FA
film has Luke face Darth Vader and his
greater mentor together with an
escalation and then succeed. Um, this is
if you can look at a character arc in
this way, what is the thing that you can
get a small victory on in the first
book? Luke defeats Darth Vader by
outflying him and having better friends
than him. Basically, um, Luke defeats
Darth Vader because Han shows up at the
last moment and Luke learns to use the
force. he has defeated Darth Vader and
blown up the Death Star, but obviously
the bigger challenge is still there. Um,
and having a character have a victory,
but also have this looming sort of I
know there's a lot that I still have to
learn that I have to deal with and uh
and whatnot for a future book is um is
relevant. And the longer you go in a
series, the more you may want to be able
to move external conflict to replacing
that. A character arc uh does not have
to be, you know, completely internal. Uh
there can be lots of things involving
the external arcs and indeed uh at the
same time you can also have characters
you know learn small things in the same
way that an iconic character does go
through experiences become a different
person. Uh James Bond is a different
person at the end of every book. It's
just that you don't need to have all of
that meaning to put context everything.
Um I really do like how the uh Daniel
Craig movies uh did this. They have just
enough continuity that there that
earlier books are meaningful, but Bond
doesn't have to go through an arc
explicitly in each of them. He goes
through one in a couple of them. Um, so
anyway, there's some talk about that. It
is I'm glad you're asking this question.
Um, when you are working on sequels,
this is one of the more important things
to be considering. You want to avoid
having the character learn the same
thing every time, but also you want to
avoid having the character um always
have to be going through some very
difficult arc. Um you sometimes want
them to do different things. So uh good
question. How do you balance out a
character taking risks with the readers
just calling them idiots when something
goes wrong? Excellent question,
especially when the stakes can be very
high. For some more context, I have a
character who is very competent, but I
want to have them take a risk and
miscalculate how dangerous it is because
they're trying to act quickly.
Specifically, they're trying to save a
kid and fail to protect themselves, uh,
which can have known catastrophic
effects. Uh, the, uh, reader doesn't
know the exact effect, but being first
person, the characters realizing the
disaster as they're failing. Um, I think
you're probably going to be okay with
that one. I will just tell you. Uh, this
is a good question.
Um, you do want to balance the
character's incompetence and their
likability in general at the beginning
of a story. Uh, having a character be
incompetent in a few areas incompetent
in a few other areas. Having them take
risks and having those risks have
consequences is good. I think you've
already kind of got it here, right? A
character has to act quickly. They
cannot make their decision. Uh, and
particular if you foreshadowed this is a
character who's bad at making decisions
quickly. They're really good at making
decisions if they have the time and
maybe over the course of the story they
are learning how to make, you know, how
to not freeze up or maybe it's just a
bad situation and there's no character
arc here. Uh, sometimes you make the
wrong call. Uh, a lot will depend on how
other characters respond to this
character. Um, and initially having
other characters be like, "You screwed
that up. I can't believe you screwed
that up." But then having somebody kind
of wise and more knowledgeably be like
this happens. We have to make judgment
calls last minute. Sometimes they'll be
wrong, but if we don't make a call, it's
always wrong. So you did your best. And
kind of having that or having the
character come to that decision is one
way. Again, control the reader's um
focus by what the story focuses upon. If
you get bad feedback or if you get
feedback on this that is good feedback
but says that people are really thinking
this character is dumb. Well then either
add some more foreshadowing that this
could possibly be a problem again. Hang
a lantern on it so to speak so that the
readers when it fails say okay I saw
this coming. It was foreshadowed. Let's
see how the character handles it. That
is a way to take off the edge on some of
that. making sure the character is
competent in other areas so that when
they fail in an area like this, it um it
doesn't hit quite so hard or hinging
your whole story around this big failure
and having the character earn back our
trust through the course of it. These
are all perfectly valid ways. Um this
reads like one that's going to work to
me. Um, what you want to avoid, the big
danger with this is having a character
make a big mess for everyone else at the
beginning of a story in a way that turns
us off to liking them. Uh, that's a
danger and you you got to be careful
about those things. It's reason why a
lot of the the things that characters
flub at the beginnings of stories don't
directly impact characters we love and
that the stakes aren't too high and the
costs aren't too high. But you know
there there is a question here. Uh you
know one of the issues I have with the
way Shadow and Bone was handled uh which
as I recall was not handled uh this way
quite uh the same way in the in the
books is you know the main character
makes a very big mistake in uh the first
or second episode and it's explicitly
kind of for selfish reasons. This is a
hard thing to work back from. You
totally can and I think season one of
Shadow Bone is really excellent and I
think that they do but that was a very
dangerous move and you know there are
things you could have done to that show
to just not make it seem so selfish.
Basically she insists that uh you know a
certain thing happened and then a
disaster happens because of that if you
could have made they would have made it
so that she insisted upon that for
reasons that didn't feel quite so
selfish. Watch for that selfishness. uh
a character being selfless and things
messing up, we're going to take way
better than the character being selfish.
Uh even if that's a character flaw, if
it is a character flaw, own it and then
uh then recoup it as the uh as the story
progresses. You can do dangerous things.
You can do things that um early on would
that people would say this is a mistake
because if you own them and you make
your story about them, they will then be
hallmarks of your story. Don't try to
write a story that everyone is going to
love. write the piece of art that you
want to write. But do be aware that
that's a danger um that you know you you
want to do intentionally, not
accidentally. When writing multiple
viewpoints, how do you know when a scene
should be written from one perspective
or another? How do you decide which
viewpoint is better suited to a scene?
Uh generally, rule of thumb, character
taking the
actions, character um that has the most
investment and emotional stake, um
character going through the most pain.
Uh, watch for those things when picking
your viewpoint character. You can't
always do that. Um, and sometimes it is
interesting to have an external
viewpoint, but watch for those external
viewpoints on interesting things
happening. Try to if you're doing
multiple viewpoints and they're all
viewpoint characters, put us in the head
of the person acting.
Um, this again is a rule of thumb. One
out of 10 times you'll want to do it the
other way for artistic or storytelling
reasons. Uh sometimes you talk about set
it setting being its own character like
Arachus or a town in 100 the town in 100
years of solitude. Uh does this happen
intentionally and does it follow the
same rules?
Um I can't speak for Gabriel Garcia
Marquez or Frank Herbert. Uh when I do
it it's intentional. Um setting is
usually its own character but usually
deciding whether you're bringing it to
the forefront or kind of leaving it in
the background. Um, and how much are you
making the Senate have conflict uh
causing conflict for the characters? How
much is it having its own quirks and its
own flaws and limitations and handicaps
and all of these things? How are you
using the setting and how is it
impacting the characters? When I say the
setting is its own character, uh, in the
same way that the character influences
decisions of others, how is the setting
influencing the decisions of others? Um,
I do this intentionally. Um, and it
follows some of the same rules, but not
the exact same rules, right? Um, uh, I
imagine setting as a character in the
same way that I might
imagine a character who is external to
the main character who's not going to
get viewpoint, who causes a lot of
conflict and problems for the character
that they characters they must overcome.
Um, and I want to make sure that there's
quirks to them. I want to make sure that
there's advantages to living in the
setting as well as just disadvantages,
right? I want to be able to see, you
know, how the characters navigate living
in this setting and making use of the
setting or responding to or against the
setting, whether it be Iraqis or whether
it be the religious climate or whatnot
of the place they live in. How do you
manage dialogue in scenes with multiple
strong willed characters? Specifically,
the people might be aligned on the
overall goal, but all of them have
slightly different motivations, and each
one believes themselves to be the leader
of the group. Um, these are fun. Uh,
what you're describing here is very fun.
Um, when you can make characters
motivations manifest through dialogue
and the way that they speak with others
and the friction points between how they
want to accomplish what they want to
accomplish, it that is often where your
characters become most clear and most
manifest. Um, and I recommend it being
something that you practice. Uh, because
generally dialogue is a better place to
do this than uh narrative. You're going
to do it in both. Uh, but dialogue tends
to be a stronger show versus tell. Um,
and being able to write great dialogue
scenes where people back and forth. Um,
you know, how do you do it? How do you
manage um dialogue in scenes? Well, uh,
I tend to go into a scene with goals. I
tend to go into a dialogue scene saying,
"Here's what I want to accomplish." And
now, um, all writing is improv. All
writing is discovery writing. at some
point uh I go in with a with a bullet
point. Dallinar is going to discuss um
with um you know this monarch about
joining his coalition. That's my bullet
point. Here's what's going to happen.
You know, I'll have the bullet point
saying he's going to get rejected. Uh
it's not going to go very well uh
because this character is like this. And
then I'll sit down and be like, "All
right, what makes this scene interesting
and dynamic? Uh what can I reveal about
Dallinar? What can I reveal about the
other character? Is there foreshadowing
I want to accomplish in this? Are there
side characters there that I can show
glimpses of that can also, you know, be
entering the conversation? And what is
their conversation showing about them
and their motivations? Um, and I I do I
bullet point a lot of this as I sit down
to write the scene. Uh, these aren't in
my outline. It's in what I kind of call
a floating outline where I just take a
list of bullet points and I say, "Okay,
I'm gonna try this. These are my goals.
This is what I want to accomplish." And
then I'll sit and I'll free form it. Uh,
I'll improv it. uh and and see how the
scene goes. At the end of the scene,
after writing it, I might have had
things that that didn't go as well as I
wanted. I'll usually bullet point those
at the top of the scene um for revision
later. Sometimes I'll go back and I'll
fix them right then. Usually, I'll
bullet point them as long as they're
kind of small things for things to try
on a reread. So, what is the role of
iconic characters when they are
something other than the protagonist?
Can iconic characters who've already
learned their lesson help the
protagonist learn and grow? And how does
that relationship work in fiction? Are
there roles that iconic characters are
very well suited for in a story? Uh,
wow, that's really cool. I'm glad you're
thinking about that. Uh, the answer to
all of that is of course yes. U, but
let's dig into it a little bit. Um, what
is the role of iconic characters? We've
already learned um that when they are
something other than the protagonist.
Uh, iconic characters do make excellent
villains, right? Uh, you generally are
not going to be showing viewpoints from
your villain. Um, generally meaning like
60% of the time, 40% of the time you
will be. Um, but they won't necessarily
have something to learn. Uh, and if you
treat them like a character, like I kind
of talked about, um, you can have them
kind of learn the lesson, but then
refuse at the end. And that's part of
what makes them a villain. Um, but they
can also, uh, be somebody who, you know,
has had their chances and is now
determined, uh, to accomplish what
they're going to accomplish. Um, and uh,
you can go both directions. uh Gollum in
the Lord of the Rings uh films in
particular, you know, is struggling with
an arc. He's uh he's less iconic, but uh
he eventually makes that that failed
decision. But I would say that uh in the
Dark Knight, um Joker is an excellent
example of an iconic character as a
villain. He has made his decisions. He's
already come up with his life
philosophy. He already has his flaws.
Batman manifests those flaws to him
through their conflict, but he does not
change. and um that you know that's
where his downfall happens. Uh he laughs
about and says oh we're just going to
keep doing this because we won't change.
Um but through the course of that story
Batman does change. Batman does learn
and he doesn't. So that contrast is
really cool. Um can iconic characters
have already learned their lessons help
the protagonist learn and grow? I mean
you are outlining what the mentor
character usually is. It depends.
Obviously in Misborn, Kelsier is not an
iconic character um and things like
that, but you know, in a lot of stories,
Gandalf is iconic, right? Gandalf is not
changing. Uh Frodo's on a downward arc
through the course of Lord of the Rings.
He is being corrupted by the ring. He is
doing his best, but it is slowly
destroying him. And Gandalf has already
made that decision. He does not accept
the ring. He's refused it. Um he
continues to be Gandalf. his evolution
of a character happens kind of to him
rather than because of him. He fights
the balro and is reborn um because sends
him back um and things like this. So
Gandalf is there for wisdom and for
learning. He's known he's he's learned a
lot of things. He knows a lot of things.
Um and you'll find that your uh your
mentor figure is often an iconic
character, but you know, a lot of your
sidekicks are iconic characters. Uh the
Mission Impossible films uh is a really
interesting series film series because I
feel they get better and better as they
go along which is odd. Uh you don't
usually have a series running that long
where your strongest entries are like
films you know seven and eight or
whatnot. Uh I I reserve judgment on Dead
Reckoning till I see the second half of
it. But until dead reckoning, I feel
that each film got stronger with perhaps
a little dip for film 2. Uh as much as I
love Jamlu, um so but in that series, I
would say most of the team do not have
arcs. There are iconic characters whose
job is to be there to do their stick, to
make us laugh now and then uh to give us
some emotion. uh because the majority of
the time is spent on Ethan Hunt and
usually one villain and one um one
secondary main protagonist um who are
often going through some interesting arc
uh and I think those films are excellent
because of that and you can see that the
role of the side characters being to
offer some continuity um and just some
fun. So, uh, there's three re reasons
why you might want to use iconic, uh,
characters other than your protagonist.
In any tips for troubleshooting when
your main character becomes less
interesting/lovable than your supporting
characters. Oh man, this is this is a
problem uh that you will run into. Uh,
this is in part because you'll be giving
these weird quirks to your side
characters and uh, oftentimes you forget
to do so with your main character. Um, I
could suppose I could reconsider whom I
choose for my main viewpoint character,
but I find that I repeatedly end up
loving my supporting characters more
than most of the in more most of the
stories I've written so far. All right,
so this is a good problem to be having.
Uh, it means you can write uh
interesting and uh quirky characters.
Um, I would say that um I encountered
this in the early draft of the Wax and
Wayne novels where Wayne was more
interesting um than Wax was. This is in
part because of things that make Wayne a
good sidekick that it's kind of the Jack
Sparrow problem. Uh if Wayne had
headlined the books, actually I tried
writing the first book about Wayne when
it was a short story. Um the weirdness
is too much and it's one of these things
like rich milk chocolate. They're
getting in um getting in small doses uh
is actually makes them a stronger
character. Having one or two Wayne
viewpoints per book really makes him pop
as a character and lets him have arcs
that are interesting, but if it were all
Wayne all the time, I think you would
just get tired of him. Um, and so, uh, I
wrote the first book and Wax was kind of
bland by comparison. What I realized was
I had not given, uh, Wax a really strong
motivation for being there. Um I had not
um you know like um
the uh this is when I sat down and I put
in uh what happened uh a lot of the
stuff in Shadows of Self um are things I
came up with to add as foreshadowing in
book one because I knew I needed more
for Wax. That's when it became a series
when I was doing the revisions. And
because of that, I added um a much
bigger arc about why he left, why he
came back, what he's hoping to
accomplish, who he is, and I I'm like,
what are Wax's flaws? Uh he what what
what is he working on? What are his
problems? Um and I had to work on this
idea that, you know, Wax approaches
problems too analytically sometimes. Uh
he forgets the people involved. And this
let me have him have a flaw uh that I he
could work on. It let me uh have him uh
have an arc which made him really much
more interesting. Uh and it gave him
investment and stakes in what was
happening. Um and you know it let him
have some quirks. Let your main
characters have some of those quirks. Uh
like I said, a character like Wayne,
sometimes they can headline um but
sometimes they're better in supporting.
But learn the lessons from what you're
doing with your side characters. Uh this
is this is a problem when someone
decides I want to make a character
strong. I'm gonna make a cool strong
character. They make them an absolute
badass and then don't make them flawed
in any interesting way. Uh and so they
become bland. Um you know it is it is
the Harry Potter problem. Uh less about
him being awesome and more about him
being you know he's the viewpoint
through which we see the story but then
his uh other characters um his his two
friends are more interesting to him.
Well he can have some more flaws, some
more quirks. Um, so, uh, look at that.
Uh, see what you're doing with those
side characters that, uh, that is
working. How can you avoid repeating a
character's name too often? Especially
when I have a lot of scenes with two,
uh, male characters, I find you need to
name them very frequently to avoid
confusion. This be avoided by improving
characterization or using traits in
place of names. Um, just use the name.
Uh, don't stress this. Uh, this name is
largely invisible, uh, except as a
marker to the reader. uh don't worry
about it unless you're getting a lot of
complaints. Um but if you have pronoun
fluency, um you're going to be using the
name uh often because anytime you use a
pronoun, you need to make sure it's
referencing back to the most recent uh
noun that it could be referencing. Uh
and if you don't do this, your writing
will just be unclear. Uh so I would say
don't stress this unless you're getting
just a ton of feedback uh that you're
using the the character's name too
often. And if you are um I mean in that
case you may look at your dialogue
sequences that are just between two
characters and when they're between two
characters you can uh cut the
attributions um more often. Uh you can
look at starting paragraphs with the
character's name and then using a
pronoun for the rest of of that
paragraph. But just make sure you you
have you're fluent with your pro uh
pronouns. You don't want to be confusing
people with those. So uh my gut is don't
stress this. Uh can I talk about how
Robin Hobb uses characters to guide her
story and why it is so effective. She
puts them through much through so much
they make bad choices but in so many uh
but so many love her characters. How
does she get that kind of dimension? Uh
how do you get that kind of dimension?
Uh I mean Robin Hobb is one of the
greatest living uh writers. Uh and so uh
how do you do it like Robin Hobb um is a
bigger answer than I can give right
here. Uh but maybe a few tips. One of
the things that Robin Hobb focuses on
her in her books is really authentic
real life living for her characters. Uh
she doesn't skip the parts that a lot of
us skip when we're writing action uh
stories. She goes into the daily life.
And so you have signed up for that by
reading one of her books. You have self-
selected to be a crowd that is okay. Uh
that you're going to see daily life and
the struggles of daily life. It's not
boring because the characters having
conflict and problems and things like
this, but you're getting a lot more of
that so that as the struggles happen,
you've bonded to these characters
because they are so real. And I think
that authenticity and realism is the
thing that uh makes her books uh shine.
Uh when people put down a Robin Hood
book is because um there's so much of
that that they don't feel that the story
is moving the way that they would want.
Um, and you know, every book is going to
have things that appeal to some readers
and not others. Uh, but if you like
Robin Hobb's uh writing, and I do, and I
think, uh, she is fantastic. Um, I would
say make us feel that the car that
things are authentic. She does put her
characters through a ton. They do make
terrible choices, but because their
motivations are so wellestablished and
who they are is so well established and
those motivations feel real, um then
they feel like our friends who are
making mistakes rather than a character
in a film who's doing uh something
stupid, if that makes sense. So, uh
yeah, you can definitely uh spend a lot
of time studying Robin Hob and I would
recommend you do so. uh particularly
kind of the later Fitz and Fool books um
and just kind of showing how a character
grows up and changes and how daily life
can be fascinating. Uh she's very good
at that. So uh there you go. Uh there's
your uh Q&A on uh character. Thank you
so much. I realize there's a bunch of
them we didn't get to. Um but uh
hopefully this will give you some
springboards into finding some of those
answers on your own because of course
the answer to most questions is practice
a whole bunch. see how professionals
have done it, try it yourself, and uh
work your way through it, and hopefully
that will bring you your answers. And
again, writing advice isn't
onesizefits-all. I um I have one
perspective. I try to give lots of
perspectives, but it's all going to be
clouded by the way that I uh write
books. So, if you have advice to people
that has worked for you on any of these
points, um please put them in the
comments. Uh get us a different
perspective. Let us know what's working
for you. uh answers to these questions
that might give a different perspective
from the one that I've given um so that
people who ask the questions can dive in
and uh see what is working for other
authors who are writing like they are.
Uh we will do the worldbuing Q&A next.
So if you haven't left your questions on
the uh last worldbuing lecture, go do so
now and we will pick say 10 of them and
do another one of these.